<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The causes for vvhich the most high and mighty prince and lo: Lord Gustavus Adolphus of the Swedes, Gothes, and Vandals King great Prince of Finland, Duke of Esthonia and Carelia, and Lord of Ingria, is at length constrained to move with an armie into Germany. Translated out of the Latine copy.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1631</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02403</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12532</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118985</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854192</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854192</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19601</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02403)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19601)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1069:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The causes for vvhich the most high and mighty prince and lo: Lord Gustavus Adolphus of the Swedes, Gothes, and Vandals King great Prince of Finland, Duke of Esthonia and Carelia, and Lord of Ingria, is at length constrained to move with an armie into Germany. Translated out of the Latine copy.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by G. Purslowe] for Nath. Butter, and Nicholas Bourne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1631.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>For another translation see STC 12535.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gustav, --  II, Adolf, --  King of Sweden --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Europe --  History --  1517-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Thirty Years' War, 1618-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19601:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19601:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CAVSES FOR VVHICH The moſt high and mighty Prince and Lo: <hi>LORD</hi> GVSTAVUS ADOLPHUS <hi>Of the</hi> Swedes, Gothes, <hi>and</hi> Vandals <hi>King,</hi> Great Prince of <hi>Finland,</hi> Duke of <hi>Eſthonia</hi> and <hi>Carelia,</hi> and Lord of <hi>Ingria,</hi> Is at length conſtrained to move with an Armie into <hi>Germany.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of the Latine Copy.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Nath. Butter,</hi> and <hi>Nicholas Bourne.</hi> 1631.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:19601:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19601:2"/>
            <head>The Cauſes for which the moſt high and mighty Prince and Lord, <hi>LORD</hi> GVSTAVUS ADOLPHUS Of the <hi>Swedes, Gothes,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>andals</hi> King, Great Prince of <hi>Finland,</hi> Duke of <hi>Eſthonia</hi> and <hi>Carelia,</hi> and Lord of <hi>Ingria,</hi> Is at length conſtrained to move with an Armie into <hi>Germany.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Is an old ſaying, No man has peace longer than he pleaſe his enemy. How true it is, his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty of <hi>Swedeland</hi> theſe late yeers hath had expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, and yet daily has, to his great damage. For although ſince his raigne, he has not been more carefull of any thing, than to conſerve love &amp; amity with all his neighbours, and ſpecially the States of <hi>Germany,</hi> whereby peace and tranquility might flouriſh every where, commerce and other Trades in time of peace be put in uſe for the benefit of each Nation, yet could he not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine any thing, but that greater treacheries were plotted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him yeare by yeare, by thoſe diſturbers of the common Peace, which had with fire and ſword waſted almoſt all <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many.</hi> His Majeſty indeed was long ſince adviſed, and that not by a few of the States of <hi>Germany,</hi> that he ſhould looke to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe betimes, while the fire was yet burning in high <hi>Germany;</hi> and ſhould not expect they would be ere a whit more friendly to him if they came neerer: but that he ſhould preſently take
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19601:3"/>
armes, come into <hi>Germany,</hi> and by a joint power help to quench the flame: being aſſured, his owne houſe was in danger, if his neighbours were on fire. Neither did his Majeſty want then, either a good occaſion; the imitation of the inhabitants, the inſtigation of forraigners: or a juſt cauſe; his friends and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates oppreſſed, who ſo earneſtly required his ayd and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour. Yet becauſe he alwaies hoped, they would at length be more moderate, than ſo madly to inſult on his poore harmleſſe neighbourhood; meaſuring their actions by his owne diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he choſe rather to commend his owne welfare awhile to Gods goodneſſe, and the uprightneſſe of his owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, than to doe any thing raſhly or unadviſedly.</p>
            <p>But when <hi>Anno</hi> 1626. in thoſe warres between him and the King and Kingdome of <hi>Polonia,</hi> he went into <hi>Pruſia</hi> a province of that Kingdome, and beganne more neerely to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, what he might promiſe himſelfe of thoſe Incendiaries of <hi>Germany:</hi> he then found the advice of his friends was true, and the neerer his enemies came to the provinces bordering on the Baltique Sea, the more and greater every day occaſions of quarrell were ſtill pickt againſt him. For firſt the ſame yeere againſt the law of Nations, they intercepted and broke open his Majeſties packet to the Prince of <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> put the Meſſenger in priſon, and to get his Majeſties ill will, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht his Letters in a forged tranſlation. Then, when there was good hope of compoſing thoſe long controverſies betweene <hi>Sweden</hi> and <hi>Poland</hi> by friendly treaties; Commiſſioners of each Kingdome meeting yeere by yeere: yet thoſe turbulent ſpirits ſo wrought by their Letters and Meſſengers, againe and againe into <hi>Poland,</hi> that there ſhould be no peace with <hi>Swedeland,</hi> till they had workt their owne ends in the Empire; hoping that the Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> being brought in ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Pole would intreat their helpe for the ſubduing of <hi>Swedeland.</hi> And that they might bee as good as their words, and by all meanes poſsible, weaken <hi>Swedeland</hi> and ſtrengthen the Pole, they did not onely hinder his Majeſty of bringing men and munition out of <hi>Germany,</hi> and yet gave way to the Pole for the ſame, being his enemy: but alſo, when this ſeem'd too little (for elſewhere and out of <hi>Germany</hi> it ſelfe in deſpight of them his Majeſty had ſouldiers enow) preſently the next yeere 1627. they ſent the Duke of <hi>Holſteyn</hi> with a great Army
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19601:3"/>
againſt him into <hi>Pruſia:</hi> and that not under his owne or the Poles, but under the Emperours Standard.</p>
            <p>Nor yet were they content with this hoſtitity, but to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive the Kingdome of <hi>Sweden</hi> of all commerce with men, they not onely unjuſtly ſpoild his Majeſties poore ſubjects com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming on the <hi>German</hi> ſhoare to trade, taking away their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, and confiſcating their Shippes: but alſo did the ſame too by their agents at <hi>Lubeck</hi> and the other <hi>Hanſ-townes,</hi> under colour indeed to reſerve thoſe commodities for them onely; but indeed, that they might take them from the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the Kingdome of <hi>Swedeland,</hi> and ſo by this meanes get a Navy together, whereby they might belch out their venome upon the Baltique Sea: as the next yeere following they more openly made knowne under thoſe monſtrous titles of Generall of the Seas, and by poſſeſsing themſelves as well of the inland places of ſtrength, as of the Sea coaſt and ports of all <hi>Mechle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> and <hi>Pomerania.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which let a man, that can, thinke ſhould have been put up, and to avoid medling in other mens matters, might have been paſt over, as long as they kept themſelves in the Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent: but after that they made choiſe of the Soundt for harbor of their Pyracy, and ſpread themſelves upon the Sea: by how much twas a greater prejudice to all States that any way tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in thoſe parts, by ſo much the leſſe was it to be endured by the Kings of <hi>Swedeland:</hi> ſpecially ſince the guard of thoſe Seas have anciently belonged to thoſe Kings.</p>
            <p>Now when his Majeſty grew ſo much the warier, aſwell by the conſideration of theſe injuries, as the former adviſes of his friends, and the next ſpring againe paſſed over into <hi>Pruſia,</hi> thinking of nothing more, than to accommodate theſe incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences in a faire courſe: It happened that there came Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours to his Majeſty into <hi>Pruſia</hi> from the Towne of <hi>Stralſund,</hi> who grievouſly complained, that although their poore Towne had committed nothing either againſt the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, or Empire, or any State of the Empire, for which it was ſo farre from being ever cited or accuſed, or convicted, or condemned, that it was declared innocent by the Imperiall decree, and aſſured of the raiſing of the Army that lay before it, notwithſtanding ſuch was the villany of the enemies army, that in deriſion of its innocence, in deſpight of the Imperiall
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19601:4"/>
conſtitutions and priviledges, in contempt of <hi>Arnheimbius</hi> truce made with thoſe of <hi>Pomerland,</hi> in neglect of many other treaties of former times (by all which they thought they were moſt ſafely provided for) nor yet conſidering the unjuſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action and payment of ſo much money, gifts and preſents, nor the breach of both religious and politick peace: notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all theſe, the ſaid Armie principally waſted the Countrey adjoyning, built forts about the Towne, ſurprized the Iland <hi>Dehnholm</hi> lying over againſt the harbour, without any denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of hoſtility, and fortified it to their prejudice; blockt up all the paſſages forward and backward from the Continent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Rugia,</hi> from the Towne into the continent; deluded the Citizens with many mock-treaties, commanded them Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons when they had been exhauſted with huge payments, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired their harbour and Ships and Ordnance: and when at length they were denyed all theſe by the free Citty, they cloſely beſieged the Towne, and moſt unworthily perſecuted it with fire and ſword even to the laſt.</p>
            <p>When as then the Emperours edicts tooke no place, the Duke of <hi>Pomerland</hi> forſooke them, and they were given for loſt by the <hi>Hans-townes:</hi> by the law of Nations, by vertue of their liberties, and after the example of their Anceſtours, they being forc't to entreat helpe from a forraigne power, till this ſuddaine tempeſt was overpaſt, they entertained, and but a while, the troopes of the King of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> being ready at hand, for the withſtanding the furiouſneſſe of this firſt aſſault. And leſt this afterward might prove prejudiciall to them, as if they had joyned with the Emperours enemies, they had no other fairer or readier courſe, than to put their liberties under protection of the King of <hi>Swedeland</hi> as an indifferent and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate Prince.</p>
            <p>His Maje. therfore of <hi>Swedeland,</hi> conſidering ſpecially, that his friends could not now promiſe any good to themſelves from the vaſt projects of ſo hoſtile an Army: with all obſerving that the requeſt of this afflicted Towne was grounded both on God and mans Law; and upon that bond of obſervance and neighbourhood, of the ſame religion and liberty, and free trade, wherein they were alwaies devoted as to his predeceſſours the Kings and Kingdome of <hi>Swedeland,</hi> ſo unto himſelfe: and laſtly, in what danger not onely himſelfe, and the Kingdome
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19601:4"/>
of <hi>Swedeland,</hi> but all the neighbouring States be, if any private mans ambition ſhould ſet up a <hi>Rendevous</hi> for Pyrates in this harbour: He could not by any meane refuſe, but ſend ayd to the oppreſſed, that ſo earneſtly deſired his helping hand, both for his friends and neighbours ſake, as alſo for his owne ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard and the publike peace.</p>
            <p>By which reſolution of his, though it came to paſſe, that both <hi>Caeſars</hi> edicts had their full authority; and the Baltique Sea was yet ſafe for all Nations that had any commerce with it; and the Towne of <hi>Stralſund</hi> by meanes of Majeſties friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mediation, was freed from the Garriſons of the King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> (at that time being enemies) and was reſtored both to his owne liberty and the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire (as thoſe treaties with the Citie concerning this matter doe plainely manifeſt) yet was it ſo farre from obtaining that theſe diſturbers of the Peace would remit any thing of their hoſtile attempts and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, that they were the more afterward inraged, &amp; ſet upon its utter ruine both by Sea and land. For when they ſaw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves put beſide that harbour, they ſet upon <hi>Wiſmar</hi> and other ports: nor were they content with their owne, but called a Navy from <hi>Dantz</hi> enemies of <hi>Swedeland,</hi> to joyne with them, and began ſo to rob on that Sea, that his Majeſty at laſt was forc't, if hee would have his Sea and trading ſafe, to blocke them up there with his owne Navy at his great coſt and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, untill that yeere were ſafely paſt.</p>
            <p>And that his Majeſtie of <hi>Swedeland</hi> might not remit any of his care and ſtudy of the peace and quiet of theſe nations, but trie all meanes to bring them to a friendly agreement: as ſoone as he heard of a meeting appointed at <hi>Lubeck</hi> in the beginning of the yeare 1629. for treating a peace betweene the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and the King of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> he thought fit alſo to ſend his Embaſſadours thither, who might both accommodate this buſineſſe of the Towne of <hi>Stralſund,</hi> and compoſe other jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies hence ariſen; and withall what they could by their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation bring the treatie it ſelfe to a good end. For he thought with himſelfe, that ſince moſt of thoſe jealouſies grew by occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the warre betweene the Emperour &amp; the king of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke,</hi> there could bee no peace concluded with the King of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> if <hi>Stralſund</hi> were excluded, nor yet that Citie bound to any conditions, if it ſelfe were not comprehended;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19601:5"/>
by reaſon of mutuall treaties with that towne of that matter.</p>
            <p>But though the K. of <hi>Denmarke</hi> willingly admitted of this Ambaſſage, and the other party was as friendly deſired to doe the ſame, yet was his Majeſties faire carriage ſo requited, that his ſolemne Ambaſſage was not onely received, or vouchſafe any anſwere ſo much as by letters, but withall had the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe with a ſtrange affront: and was commanded upon peril of what might befall them, to forbeare not onely <hi>Lubecke,</hi> but the whole continent of <hi>Germany</hi> alſo.</p>
            <p>Which one affront, though it has ever beene eſteemed by all nations worthy of the higheſt revenge, and there was no cauſe but that the ſharpeſt remedies ſhould be uſed: yet ſeeing the Emperours Commiſsioners, in <hi>March</hi> after, the King of <hi>Swedens</hi> were called home, tooke notice of his Majeſties let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Embaſſage by other letters, wherein by way of excuſe they ſeemed to mollifie the harſhneſſe of their former ſentence his Majeſtie alſo was willing to thinke it proceeded rather from ſome bad Counſellours than a publike reſolution: and would not yet thinke it ſufficient, though layd to the former, to put two States in a combuſtion of warre. Specially ſince the Commiſsioners withall ſignified that they had no commiſsion to treate with any but the King of <hi>Denmarke:</hi> although they certainely knew, that if the matter might be referred to the Emperour or Duke of <hi>Fridland,</hi> they ſhould receive ſuch an anſwere as would give ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>And now his Majeſtie thought it not fit to let his patience ſo many wayes wronged, hee farther abuſ'd by ſuch ſcornefull proceedings; withall conſidered whether or no, and how the partie injured might referre the buſineſſe to the Emperour (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene whom &amp; the Emperour there was not formerly wont to be any ſuch correſpondence) all the paſſages in the Empire being ſtopt, and the meeting at <hi>Lubecke</hi> now drawing to an end. Yet leſt any labour might bee ſpared, or difficultie hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the publike good, all conſiderations to the contrary layd aſide, his Majeſtie was at length ſo farre perſwaded by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of <hi>Swedeland,</hi> that preſently in <hi>April</hi> he ſhould not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly write to the Colledge of Electors, (the maine pillar of the Romane Empire, whom ſuch proceedings with forreine Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces was thought much to diſpleaſe) and wiſh them to adviſe of ſome convenient remedies, but ſhould alſo conſent, that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19601:5"/>
there ſhould be one ſent from the ſame Parliament to the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of the Armie, to trie whether thoſe controverſies which were riſen betweene the two Armies might not bee taken up by a meeting of both. Preſently there was diſpatcht his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Chamberlaine the Lord <hi>Steno Bielke,</hi> Lord Baron in <hi>Kro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenem,</hi> with Commiſsion that if hee found the adverſe partie inclined to peace, he ſhould cauſe a ceſſation of Armes for the Citie of <hi>Stralſund,</hi> untill further preparatives for a treaty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſpatcht more Commiſsioners ſhould follow, which ſhould make a finall end of the whole matter.</p>
            <p>But when at the beginning of the Spring he came to <hi>Stral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſund,</hi> and found all things worſe: former hoſtilities not onely not layd aſide, but daily increaſed with new ones: <hi>Stralſund</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſince aſſaulted, all the Ports ready provided to rob the <hi>Sweden</hi> Sea: and that which is moſt deteſtable, a compleate Armie, without any denouncing of warre ſent a ſecond time into <hi>Pruſia,</hi> and that under the conduct of <hi>Arnhembius,</hi> the Emperours Marſhall of the field. This ſudden change as twas fit, ſtopt his farther proceedings. Yet that he would not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether neglect his inſtructions, hee wrote to the Duke of <hi>Frid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> for what cauſe hee was diſpatcht, proteſted againſt the injurie of the Armie, and required both it and other hoſtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties might bee ſtopt, if the anſwere of the Commiſsioners of <hi>Lubecke</hi> ſhould goe for honeſt.</p>
            <p>But the Duke of <hi>Fridland</hi> was ſo far from recalling his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, or ſhewing any readineſſe to treat; that for greater ſcorne, hee made it good that the anſwers of his under-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioners were but plaine mockings: contending that hee could not call backe his Armie, chiefly becauſe the Emperour had ſo many ſoldiers, that he was faine to disburthen himſelfe by this Armie of <hi>Arnhembius,</hi> &amp; therefore ſent him not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe to his friend the King of <hi>Poland</hi> againſt <hi>Swedeland.</hi> Neyther beſide this would hee anſwer any thing more to the purpoſe to the iterated demands of the Embaſſadour: But made the ſaid Armie haſten their journey, who fought ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly all the laſt Summer in <hi>Pruſia</hi> againſt his Majeſtie and kingdome of <hi>Sweden,</hi> that except God the juſt avenger of all villany, had turnd their wicked deſignes on their owne heads, his Majeſtie and kingdome of <hi>Swedeland</hi> with all their friends had beene in no ſmall danger.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:19601:6"/>Can yet any man doubt whether his Majeſtie had cauſe enough to lay aſide all thoughts of peace, and take up Armes, and prepare himſelfe for battle in his owne and his confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates defence?</p>
            <p>There is one thing yet which might ſeeme a little to hinder the haſtening of this warre, and that was the expecting an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer from the Colledge of Electors to the Kings letters, &amp; alſo the mediation of the King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> (upon his Majeſties in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timation) who had already begun aſſoone as Winter was paſt to preſſe this matter for a treaty. For as long as by treating their could be any ſatisfaction made for injuries paſt, or cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on had for the future ſafegard of the neighbouring territories: his Majeſtie was never ſo thirſtie after revenge, but that out of his zeale to the common good and publike peace, hee would willingly ſuffer the cauſe to bee ended by Treatie rather than by Armes.</p>
            <p>But ſeeing from the beginning of <hi>April</hi> 1630. what time a day was appointed at <hi>Dantz</hi> in <hi>Pruſia<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> even to this moneth of <hi>June,</hi> there has beene no ſignification of a treatie made by the party injuring to the Commiſsioner of the party injured (who was there preſent, &amp; ſent his readineſſe &amp; commiſsion to treat as far as <hi>Dantz</hi> by letters) how truly the publike peace is deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, may hence undoubtedly bee gathered. Specially, ſince the affronts of former times &amp; theſe which they have offered ſince the ſending of their Commiſsioners to <hi>Dantz</hi> (by poſſeſsing the ſtrongeſt places and paſſages in <hi>Germany,</hi> and more fiercely providing themſelves to warre than afore times) doe plainly tell us, with what ſafetie ſuch a treatie is to be truſted.</p>
            <p>As for the Colledge of Electors, it might have done verie much in this cauſe, &amp; his Majeſtie is perſwaded it would have done, had the ancient libertie of the States of the Empire been preſerved, and the power of ſome Male-contents not taken ſo deepe root, that it ſeemes willing to refuſe all remedy at home. It commended indeed in their late anſwer (which was intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>Stockholm</hi> this laſt <hi>April</hi>) the peaceable deſignes of his Majeſtie of <hi>Swedeland,</hi> and his offring a diſpatch of the cauſe, and they for their part offered the like friendſhip. But when they did not ſo much as in a word touch at the remedies of thoſe injuries, which his Majeſties Letters ſpecially required, did they not leave a neceſsitie on his Majeſty to provide fit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19601:6"/>
for himſelfe? Wherefore ſince ſo many and ſo great indignities have beene really offered his Majeſtie, his packets intercepted &amp; broke open: his Subjects, Miniſters, &amp; ſoldiers ſpoyled and taken captive: common naturall commerce in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdicted: the <hi>Pole</hi> his enemy ſo oft diſſwaded from peace: a full Armie conducted into <hi>Pruſia</hi> for his Majeſties overthrow: On the other ſide; No paſſage granted his Majeſtie, though hee did no hurt nay his friends, his neighbours and Allies for his ſake have beene oppreſſed, turnd out of their Dominions on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not quite rooted out: his Embaſſadours for peace have more than barbarouſly been ſcornefully rejected: and laſtly, a furious Armie twice ſent againſt him, and that without the leaſt cauſe or colour. Are not all theſe, nay any of them by the conſent of Nations, by the rule of reaſon, and inſtinct of Nature ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient enough to take juſt revenge, except full ſatisfaction bee made? Since in contempt of all the Baltique ports, yea and ſea it ſelfe, ſo many threats, ſuch ſtirres, ſuch preparations, are yet on foot, whereby all counſailes actions, deſignes, both by ſea and land ſeeme to have been wholly layd for his ruine. Doe they not force men though unwilling to a juſt defence: at leaſt that by the law of Armes and all Nations hee ſhould in ſome meaſure provide for his owne ſafetie?</p>
            <p>Since after ſo much triall of faire meanes, there is now no legall remedie left, nay nothing but hoſtilitie offered: Does not nature it ſelfe require to trie it out by the Sword? Since there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is no other way for his Majeſtie to provide for his owne ſafetie, but in Gods name to capitulate his owne and his Allies ſecuritie by Armes, hee would hereby leave it to the whole Chriſtian world to judge into what ſtreights hee is brought, both without deſert and unwillingly. That which is objected chiefly by covetous and ambitious men, is the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of the Towne of <hi>Stralſund:</hi> Our defence whereof yet they themſelves cauſed by ſo many former hoſtile incurſions: &amp; which afterward both in point of Honour &amp; for many other reaſons his Majeſtie was perſwaded would bee much for the common peace of Germany, and the good of the Empire al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, as has beene ſaid.</p>
            <p>Had indeed his Majeſtie any way ayded eyther the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours or the Empires enemies, had hee made any truce with their foes, without juſt reſpect to them, or had hee put in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19601:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:19601:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:19601:8"/>
any deſigne tending to ther prejudice, no man could have wondred at their ſuſpition, if happily it ſhould have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned the retaliation of any ſuch revenge. But now ſeeing his Majeſtie has beene alwayes ſo conſtant to his intentions of Peace, that not onely during the warres in <hi>Germany</hi> he has in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violably kept friendſhip and ſtood Neutrall: but neither be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not ſince has given any juſt colour of offence, no not in the leaſt matters, he cannot but with griefe complaine to the whole world of ſo great indignities.</p>
            <p>Wherefore ſeeing his Majeſtie proteſts he enters not upon this warre for any prejudice of the Empire, (betweene whom and his Majeſtie there is no enmitie) but onely for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning of his owne and his Allies, and the common libertie, untill ſuch time as his friends and neighbouring confederates ſhalbe in the ſame ſtate, wherein before this war they peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and of along time flouriſhed, and that the Citie of <hi>Stral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſund,</hi> the <hi>Baltique Sea</hi> and Kingdome of <hi>Swedeland</hi> may for hereafter promiſe themſelves more ſecurity So he doubts not but the indifferent Reader, nay the ſafety onely of theſe Nations, will abhorre and deteſt the unjuſt proceedings of the adverſe party, as they truely deſerve and is confident, that the more indifferent of the German Nation, yea all Chriſtendome will favour his upright &amp; juſt way of proceeding by Armes, directed onely for a faire ſuppreſsing of ſo unjuſt a perſecution.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19601:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
